Guide to the John K. Smith papers, 1867-1924
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
John K. Smith papers 1867-1924
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Smith, John K.
.5 Linear Feet 70 Items
African American farmer and family of Meadowview (Washington County), Virginia.
Correspondence, legal, and financial papers of several generations of a rural black family in Washington County, Va., concerning personal and family matters, men working away from home, county taxes, black societies, religious activities, insurance and other topics.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John K. Smith papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1982.
Collection Overview
Correspondence and legal and financial papers from the late 19th and early 20th centuries of several generations of a rural black family in Washington County, Virginia. Topics concern personal and family matters, men working away from home, county taxes, black societies, religious activities, insurance and other topics. The financial papers in the collection document insurance investments, rental contracts, and the extent of the Smith family's land holdings in Washington County. Smith held an insurance policy with the Southern Aid Society of Virginia, and a death benefit with the Sons of Zion Benevolent Society. Letters in the collection touch on emigration, long-distance courtship, and itinerant labor.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Smith, John K.
Improved, Benevolent, Protective Order of Elks of the World
Southern Aid Society of Virginia
African American churches -- Virginia
African American clergy -- Virginia
African American farmers -- Virginia
African American fraternal organizations
African Americans -- Economic conditions
African Americans -- Organizations -- Virginia
African Americans -- Religion
African Americans -- Social conditions -- To 1964
African Americans -- Virginia -- Washington County
Farm life -- Virginia
Washington County (Va.) -- Social conditions
Virginia -- History
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1890-1923, (1 box)
  Includes both personal and business correspondence among various Smith family members and acquaintances.
  - Letter, 10 Jan., 1890, from unknown, Stump, Va., to John Smith (Box 1)
  - Letter, 11 Feb., 1891, from James Smith, Erin Springs, Rush Creek Bottom, Indian Territory [Oklahoma?], to Mr. W. W. James (Box 1)
  - Letter, 9 Jan., 1894, from Emily Barnes, Chilhowie, Va., to Mr. William Barnes (her husband) (Box 1)
  - Letter, 26 Oct. 1897, from Mrs. D. Morton, Nashville, Tenn., to John [Smith?] (Box 1)
  - Letter, 16 Dec. 1897, from Mrs. D. Morton, Nashville, Tenn., to John [Smith?] (Box 1)
  - Letter, 3 Dec., 1899, from J. K. Smith, Maybury [Mayberry?], W. Va., to Mrs. Libey Smith (his wife) (Box 1)
  - Letter, 13 Aug., 1900 from C. C. Hammer, Gauthier, Va., to Mrs. Jno Smyth [Smith?] (Box 1)
  - Letter, 5 Oct., 1900 from C. C. Hammer, Gauthier, Va., to Mrs. Smyth [Smith?] (Box 1)
  - Letter, 8 May, 1914, from Mrs. Nanie Guinon, Bristol, Va., to J. K. Smith (Box 1)
  - Letter, 14 Oct., 1923, from O.D. Harris, Roanoke, Va., to Miss Neworlins Smith (daughter of J. K. Smith) (Box 1)
- Personal Papers, 1867-1924, (1 box)
  Includes legal and financial papers, insurance policies, various receipts, and limited fraternal organization paperwork. Also includes the authorization from Pleasant Grove Baptist Church for John K. Smith to preach.
  - Handwritten preaching license for J. K. Smith from Pleasant Grove Baptist Church, 1905 July 8 (Box 1)
  - Insurance policy certificate for J. K. Smith from the Southern Aid Society of Virginia, 1919 Feb. 10 (Box 1)
  - Sons of Zion Benevolent Society payment slips, 1883-1884 and undated (Box 1)
  - Payment agreement, 1873 July 26 (Box 1)
  - Pleasant Grove Lodge Benefit Certificate for John Smith, 1883 Mar. 10 (Box 1)
  - Receipts from Reynolds Land Company, Washington County, Va. property tax payments, and Ball Bros. Furniture, 1867-1915 (Box 1)
  - Printed material: program for I.B.P.O.E. of W., Tenneva Temple, No. 282, 1924 Nov. 20 (Box 1)